Guide to the Irving McNeil Ives papers, 1862-1958
Ives, Irving McNeil papers, 1862-1958
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Irving McNeil Ives papers, 1862-1958, 1933-1958 (bulk)
1913
Irving McNeil, Ives 1896-1962.
248 cubic ft.
Correspondence, speeches, photographs, audio tapes, motion picture films, phonograph records, drawings, plans, clippings
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ives's papers, which pertain chiefly to his service in the U.S. Senate, include correspondence, memoranda, and other material from constituents, fellow legislators, executive departments, and the general public concerning appointments, bills sponsored or co-sponsored by Ives, committee hearings, education, federal agencies, commissions, and departments, foreign affairs and foreign aid, labor and public welfare, international organizations, national defense and internal security, patronage, political campaigns, public utilities, private bills, Senate bills, social security, tariff and trade agreements, taxation, transportation, veterans' affairs, and numerous other subjects. Also included are records pertaining to his years as a New York State Assemblyman; his support of his Alma Mater, Hamilton College; family and personal papers; and materials relating to Ives's insurance and banking businesses.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Politician.
Irving McNeil Ives was a member of the New York State Assembly, 1933-46; author and sponsor of legislation creating the New York State Department of Commerce and the New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Cornell University; co-author and co-sponsor of a New York State anti-discrimination law; Dean of the Industrial and Labor Relations School at Cornell, 1945-47; United States senator, 1947-59; member of the Committee on Appropriations, the Committee on Labor and Public Welfare; vice-chairman of the Senate Select Committee on Improper Activities in the Labor and Management Field, 1957; President of the International Labor Organization Conference, Geneva, 1953; Republican candidate for governor of New York, 1954.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Ives's papers, which pertain chiefly to his service in the U.S. Senate, include correspondence, memoranda, and other material from constituents, fellow legislators, executive departments, and the general public concerning appointments, bills sponsored or co-sponsored by Ives, committee hearings, education, federal agencies, commissions, and departments, foreign affairs and foreign aid, labor and public welfare, international organizations, national defense and internal security, patronage, political campaigns, public utilities, private bills, Senate bills, social security, tariff and trade agreements, taxation, transportation, veterans' affairs, and numerous other subjects. Also included are records pertaining to his years as a New York State Assemblyman; his support of his Alma Mater, Hamilton College; family and personal papers; and materials relating to Ives's insurance and banking businesses.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ives, Irving McNeil,1896-1962.; Cornell University.Board of Trustees.; New York (State).Dept. of Commerce.; New York (State).Legislature.Assembly.; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations.; United States.Congress.Senate.
Subjects:
Banks and banking.; Education--United States.; Electioneering--New York (State); Foreign trade regulation--United States.; Industrial relations--Research.; Insurance.; Legislation.; National security--Law and legislation.; Politics, Practical.; Public utilities--Law and legislation.; Public welfare--Law and legislation.; Social security--Law and legislation.; Tariff--Law and legislation.; Taxation--Law and legislation--United States.; Transportation--Law and legislation.; Veterans--United States.; Legislators.; Politicians.
Places:
United States--Armed forces.
Form and Genre Terms:
Bills (Legislative records).; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Correspondence and Legislation
Boxes 1-149, 152-158, 164, 170-181
Series II. Campaigns
Boxes 49, 70, 166, 169, 173-174, 188-190, 225, 230, 237, 239-248
Series III. Speeches
Boxes 150-151, 165-166, 182, 187-188, 205, 228, 231, 236-239, 242, 245-246, 248, 251
Series IV. Honors/Awards
Boxes 165, 170, 221, 251
Series V. Hamilton College
Boxes 5, 24, 55, 188, 246-247
Series VI. Memorabilia
Boxes 167-170, 249, 251-252
Series VII. Photographs
Boxes 159-163, 166, 171, 251
Series VIII. Audio Tapes
Box 249
Series IX. Motion Picture Films
Box 250
Series X. Phonograph Records
Box 250
Series XI. Drawings/Plans
Mapcase
Series XII. Clippings
Boxes 137, 188, 217, 224, 231, 241-243
Series XIII. Miscellany
Boxes 8, 29, 43, 50, 61, 267, 176, 188, 249, 251
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE and LEGISLATION
  - General Correspondence (Departmental Correspondence): A-Bry - 1957 (Box 1)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: veterans affairs, appointments, reducing the budget, private problems and opinions
  - General Correspondence (Departmental Correspondence): Bua-Cz - 1957 (Box 2)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: cancer research; letters to and from fellow Congressmen including: John F. Kennedy, Lyndon B. Johnson, Hubert Humphrey, George Smathers, Harry F. Byrd, and others; treatment of Protestants in Colombia, S. A.
  - General Correspondence (Departmental Correspondence): C-For - 1957 (Box 3)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: DDT used in spraying property, Father's Day, flood control, foreign affairs
  - General Correspondence (Departmental Correspondence): For-Gz - 1957 (Box 4)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: foreign affairs, gifts, greetings, Griffiss Air Force base, water wells, acquisition of property adjacent to Grumman Aircraft Corp.
  - General Correspondence: G-In - 1957 (Box 5)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Hamilton College, Alexander Hamilton Bi-centennial, highways and highway program, inauguration
  - General Correspondence: In-Maq - 1957 (Box 6)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: International Cooperation Administration, interviews, Lincoln Square project in New York City
  - General Correspondence: Mara-Oz - 1957 (Box 7)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: urging condemnation of McCarthy be stricken from record, national security, Naval Supply activities in Brooklyn transfer to Bayonne, N.J., National Grange building in Washington, New York Naval Shipyard, New York Ontario & Western Railway, New York Young Republican Club, Niagara Falls miscellany
  - General Correspondence: Pa-Rz - 1957 (Box 8)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: penicillan dosage for use with milk-producing animals; Post Office - curtailment of mail, commemorative stamps; reduction in force in defense plans; redevelopment plan
  - General Correspondence: Sa-Tz - 1957 (Box 9)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Sampson Air Force Base, camp for juvenile delinquents, Scotia Naval Supply Depot, strikes - labor disputes, tariff
  - General Correspondence: V-Z - 1957 (Box 10)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: government agencies and departments: Federal Communications, Justice and Labor Departments; also copies of letters from V-P Nixon and private bills
  - General Legislative Correspondence: January 1-24 1958 (Box 11)
    correspondence with constituents on various legislation
  - General Legislative Correspondence: January 25-February 13 - 1958 (Box 12)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: February 14-March 6 - 1958 (Box 13)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: March 7-27 - 1958 (Box 14)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: March 28-April 14 - 1958 (Box 15)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: April 15-May 1 - 1958 (Box 16)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: May 2-22 - 1958 (Box 17)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: May 23-June 20 - 1958 (Box 18)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: June 20-July 14 - 1958 (Box 19)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: July 16-August 13 - 1958 (Box 20)
  - General Correspondence: Aa-Brown - 1955 (Box 21)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: anti-aircraft artillery range near Oswego, appointments (opposition to John Marshall Harlan as Supreme Court member); broadcasts
  - General Correspondence: Bro-Dek - 1955 (Box 22)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Cuban sugar, Corsi controversy (Immigration Act of 1953); correspondence from various senators and representatives, Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Department of Justice, Civil Aeronautic Administration
  - General Correspondence: Del-Fry - 1955 (Box 23)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: flood control, Formosa, employment
  - General Correspondence: Ga-Hz - 1955 (Box 24)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: guided missile installation, Hamilton College (Ives was an alumnus and trustee)
  - General Correspondence: I-Lz - 1955 (Box 25)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Israel, Long Island Terminal and Pennsylvania Terminal employees seniority problem
  - General Correspondence: Maa-Noo - 1955 (Box 26)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: milk, N.Y.S. Republican Committee, N.Y. Central discontinuing West Shore Line, Morrocco, McCarthy censure
  - General Correspondence: Nor-Pz - 1955 (Box 27)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: personal letters to George Ives, Mrs. Marion Ives, and Senator Ives including one from John Foster Dulles, (August 30, 1955); Post Office Department and Services; potato industry
  - General Correspondence: Q-Smith - 1955 (Box 28)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Republican National Committee, reduction in force at Brooklyn (?), N. Y. Naval Shipyard, Sampson Air Force Base, Small Business Administration, Senate committees
  - General Correspondence: Sm-Tariff - 1955 (Box 29)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: stock market, tariff-miscellaneous material re H.R. 1 (1955), tariff-"Customs Simplification Act"; Tariff and Trade Agreements (letters from January-March 31st)
  - General Correspondence: Tariff-Wall - 1955 (Box 30)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: tariff and trade agreements (April-December 1955); tax bill 1955; O.N. Division of Narcotics Drugs to Geneva Transfer, U.S. Air Force and Naval Academies, copies of letters from V-P Nixon (one original copy)
  - General Correspondence: Walm-Z - 1955 (Box 31)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Washington Square South-East Project, White House correspondence (none from Eisenhower), White House Conference on Education
  - General Correspondence: Aa-Cg - 1956 (Box 32)
    correspondence with constituents
  - General Correspondence: Cha-Fek - 1956 (Box 33)
  - General Correspondence: Fel-Hop - 1956 (Box 34)
  - General Correspondence: Hor-Marr - 1956 (Box 35)
  - General Correspondence: Mars-Pez - 1956 (Box 36)
  - General Correspondence: Pf-So - 1956 (Box 37)
  - General Correspondence: Spa-Z - 1956 (Box 38)
  - General Correspondence - Special Topics: A-N - 1956 (Box 39)
  - General Correspondence - Special Topics: P-Z - 1956 (Box 40)
  - General Correspondence - Special Topics: V-Z - 1956 (Box 41)
    Political correspondence and correspondence with governmental departments and agencies, robotype correspondence
  - General Correspondence - Special Topics: Aa-Bi - 1954 (Box 42)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Flanders Res., appointment of Albert C. Beeson to NLRB, appointment of Robert E. Lee to FCC; Armed Services Medical Procurement Agency from Brooklyn; anti-aircraft artillery range near Oswego; tariff on bicycles
  - General Correspondence - Special Topics: Bla-Coy - 1954 (Box 43)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: blister rust control, Civil Aeronautics Administration, miscellaneous Congressional correspondence, copper
  - General Correspondence: Cra-Gae - 1954 (Box 44)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Federal Communications Commission (FCC)
  - General Correspondence: Gi-In - 1954 (Box 45)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: General Analine & Film Corp.; Guided Missile Center, Griffiss Air Force Base; Healthe, Education & Welfare Dept.; Housing and Home Finance Agandy; housing letters; Dept. of Interior
  - General Correspondence: Io-Lz - 1954 (Box 46)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Rabbi Abraham Kalmonowitz, Kings Point Academy, International Bank for Reconstruction & Develoment, International Labor Org.
  - General Correspondence: M-New - 1954 (Box 47)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Narcotics, Navy Dept., N.Y. National Guard, N.Y. Naval Shipyard employment situation
  - General Correspondence: Newa-Por - 1954 (Box 48)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Niagara River Power Project - Public or Private Development, nominations including letters from Dulles, NATO, Oneida County Airport, P.T.A. in Hastings, personnel, political
  - General Correspondence: Pos-Rop - 1954 (Box 49)
    political-personal answered by Mrs. Marion Ives (MMI); political campaign issues, contributions, suggestions, recount, results; political-workers, offers of assistance (governorship campaign); other political material; Post Office commemorative stamp; potato situation; Puerto Ricans; Quartermaster Purchasing Agency move from NYC to Philadelphia; Railroad Retirement Board; Republican National Committee; Rockaway Beach
  - General Correspondence: Rosa-Stt - 1954 (Box 50)
    St. Lawrence Seaway; Schenectady-Albany-Troy employment situation, Senate Committee on Rules & Administration, soil conservation reports, strikes - miscellaneous correspondence
  - General Correspondence: Stu-Va - 1954 (Box 51)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: tariff and trade agreements; Tax - H.R. 8300; Treasury Department; U.N. Charter Revision-Poll; USIA; Utica Structural Steel Corporation; V-P Nixon correspondence; White House correspondence
  - General Correspondence: Aa-Buk - 1953 (Box 52)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Dean Alfange, Esq. (Republican friend)
  - General Correspondence: Bal-Bol - 1953 (Box 53)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Thomas E. Dewey; Deepdale Gardens, Inc.; Camp Drum; Champlain College
  - General Correspondence: Dom-Grah - 1953 (Box 54)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: General Analine and Film Corp., foreign agricultural workers
  - General Correspondence: Grai-In - 1953 (Box 55)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: NLRB - Hearn Department Stores, Inc.; Hamilton College; International Bank for Reconstruction and Finance; International Laborl Organization; interviews, invitations
  - General Correspondence: Io-Lz - 1953 (Box 56)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: closing of King's Point Merchant Marine Academy
  - General Correspondence: Maa-Noq - 1953 (Box 57)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Niagara Redevelopment bill of 1953; New York, Ontario & Western Railway; Morocco Trade restrictions
  - General Correspondence: Nor-Pok - 1953 (Box 58)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Niagara River development (Carphart Martin Miller - Bill, S. 689 [Public or private development]); nominations from State Department; nominations of Mrs. Clare Luce Booth as ambassador to Italy; personal file for I.M.I. and others in his office; Plattsburgh Air Force Base
  - General Correspondence: Pol-Schk - 1953 (Box 59)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: political, Post Office - commemorative stamps, St. Lawrence Seaway, letter from Nelson Rockefeller (December 31, 1952) to Ives
  - General Correspondence: Schl-United - 1953 (Box 60)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: State Dept.
  - General Correspondence: V-Z - 1953 (Box 61)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: U.S. Army - Corps of Engineers; White House - miscellaneous correspondence
  - General Correspondence: Aa-Bz - 1952 (Box 62)
  - General Correspondence: Caa-Dz - 1952 (Box 63)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Thomas Dewey letter, December 7, 1952
  - General Correspondence: Ea-Has - 1952 (Box 64)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Reynolds Gubbin re blacklisting of Latin American firms
  - General Correspondence: Hat-Lin - 1952 (Box 65)
  - General Correspondence: Lio-Ng - 1952 (Box 66)
  - General Correspondence: Ni-Scho - 1952 (Box 67)
  - General Correspondence: S-Waz - 1952 (Box 68)
  - General Correspondence: - 1952 (Box 69)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Maurice J. Tobin, Secretary of Labor, April 3, 1952; John W. Snyder, Secretary of Treasury under Truman; Dean Acheson, Secretary of State, 1952
  - Political Correspondence: - 1952 (Box 70)
    correspondence with constituents concerning 1952 election; for and against Eisenhower and Taft; campaign correspondence
  - General Correspondence: - 1952 (Box 71)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: congratulations on reelection to Senate [arranged chronologically]
  - General Correspondence: Aa-Bri - 1951 (Box 72)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: Dean Alfange, Harold Stassen
  - General Correspondence: Bro-Daz - 1951 (Box 73)
  - General Correspondence: Dea-Gig - 1951 (Box 74)
  - General Correspondence: Gie-Jay - 1951 (Box 75)
  - General Correspondence: Je-Marz - 1951 (Box 76)
  - General Correspondence: Mas-Oz - 1951 (Box 77)
  - General Correspondence: Pa-Schl - 1951 (Box 78)
  - General Correspondence: Schm-Tho - 1951 (Box 79)
  - General Correspondence: To-Z - 1951 (Box 80)
  - Special Topics: Oer-Z - 1951 (Box 81)
    see separate list by N. P.
  - Supplemental General Correspondence: A-Z - 1951-1954 (Box 82)
  - General Legislative Correspondence and General Correspondence: Aa-Bro - 1958 (Box 83)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: legislation, departments
  - General Correspondence: Bru-Hal - 1958 (Box 84)
  - General Correspondence: Ham-Oe - 1958 (Box 85)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: letter from Averill Harriman, March 27, 1958
  - General Correspondence: Of-Won - 1958 (Box 86)
  - General Correspondence: Woo-Z; Supplemental General Correspondence: A-G - 1958 (Box 87)
    correspondence with constituents on topics including: letter from John F. Kennedy (referral to I.M.I.)
  - General Correspondence: H-R - 1958 (Box 88)
  - General Correspondence: S-Z; Special Topics: A-Con - 1958 (Box 89)
  - Special Topics: Con-I - 1958 (Box 90)
    x
  - Special Topics: J-Sz - 1958 (Box 91)
  - Special Topics: Ta-Z; Labor Legislation Correspondence - 1958 (Box 92)
  - x - 1958 (Box 93)
  - correspondence: A-G - 1958 (Box 94)
    Requests for printed matter
  - correspondence: H-R - 1958 (Box 95)
    requests for printed matter
  - correspondence: S - 1957-1958 (Box 96)
  - correspondence - 1958-1959 (Box 96)
    invitations to dinners, speaking engagements, social affairs, etc.
  - Robotype correspondence: A-H - 1958 (Box 97)
    (alphabetical by subject) correspondence with constituents on topics including: humane slaughter
  - Robotype correspondence - 1958 (Box 98)
    correspondence with constituents on topic: humane slaughter
  - Robotype correspondence: H-P - 1958 (Box 99)
  - Robotype correspondence: P-R - 1958 (Box 100)
  - Robotype correspondence R-Z - 1958 (Box 101)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: January 1-February 5 - 1957 (Box 102)
    correspondence with constituents on legislation
  - General Legislative Correspondence: February 6-27 - 1957 (Box 103)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: Feb. 27-March 19 - 1957 (Box 104)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: March 20-April 8 - 1957 (Box 105)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: April 9-May 2 - 1957 (Box 106)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: May 3-27 - 1957 (Box 107)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: May 28-June 24 - 1957 (Box 108)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: June 25-July 23 - 1957 (Box 109)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: July 24-August 21 - 1957 (Box 110)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: August 22-November 15 - 1957 (Box 111)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: November 18-December 31 - 1957 (Box 112)
  - Supplemental General Correspondence: N-Z - 1957 (Box 113)
    includes photostat of letter from President Eisenhower, November 19, 1956
  - Labor Legislation Correspondence - 1957 (Box 113-114)
    correspondence with constituents on McClellan hearings and other labor managment situations
  - Correspondence: January-December - 1957 (Box 114)
    invitations to social affairs, dinners, speaking engagements, etc.
  - Correspondence - 1957 (Box 115)
    invitations miscellaneous and unanswered
  - General Legislative Correspondence: January 1-24 - 1956 (Box 116)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: January 25-February 15 - 1956 (Box 117)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: February 16-March 8 - 1956 (Box 118)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: March 9-April 4 - 1956 (Box 119)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: April 5-28 - 1956 (Box 120)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: April 30-May 31 - 1956 (Box 121)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: June 1-27 - 1956 (Box 122)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: June 28-August 15 - 1956 (Box 123)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: August 16-31, November 1-December 28 - 1956 (Box 124)
  - Supplemental General Correspondence and General Legislative Correspondence: January-April, September-December - 1956 (Box 124)
  - Correspondence: January-September - 1956 (Box 124)
    Invitations
  - Correspondence: October-December - 1956 (Box 125)
  - Robotype Correspondence: A-G - 1956 (Box 125)
    Correspondence with constituents
  - Robotype Correspondence: G-M - 1956 (Box 126)
  - Robotype Correspondence: N-T - 1956 (Box 127)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: September 1-December 12 - 1955 (Box 128)
  - General Legislative Correspondence: December 13-30 - 1955 (Box 129)
  - Correspondence: December - 1955 (Box 129)
    invitations
  - Post Office Correspondence: A-N (alphabetical by locality) - 1955 (Box 130)
    appointment of postmasters
  - Bills and Related Correspondence - 1951-1952 (Box 131)
    Public Bills: S 101-S 2301 (bills sponsored or co-sponsored by I.M.I. arranged by Bill number); related corrrespondence
  - Bills and Related Correspondence - 1951-1952 (Box 132)
    Public Bills (Senate): S 2343-S3300, S. Con. Res. 11-77, S. Res. 52-306; Private Bills: S. 549-S.3331; Public Bills (House): HR 313; 4394-4473 (folders 1-2)
  - Bills and Related Correspondence - 1951-1952 (Box 133)
    Public Bills: H. R. 4473, Private Bills: H. R. 576-7454, H. Con. Res. 191
  - Bills and Related Correspondence - 1953-1954 (Box 133)
    Public Bills: S. 1026-1831 (All bills were referred to Labor & Public Welfare Committee; mainly Taft-Hartley amendments. Letter from Senator John F. Kennedy, July 30, 1953 re S. J. Res. 107, Kennedy et al: to increase minimum wage rates from $.75 to $1.00 under the Fair Labor Standards Act
  - Bills and Related Correspondence - 1955-1956 (Box 134)
    Labor and Public Welfare Committee: S. 205-S. 3958, S. J. Res. 46 (bills sponsored or co-sponsored by I.M.I.); related correspondence
  - Bills and Related Correspondence - 1955-1956 (Box 135)